[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software SE radio has an opening for a
volunteer host to produce five episodes
per year to apply please follow the
instructions on our website at se-
radio.net
cont welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host Jeff dittle I'm
excited to invite Steve Smith as our
guest on the show today for a
conversation about software quality
Steve is founder and principal architect
at Nimble Pros Steve has over 20 years
of experience building custom software
Solutions using Microsoft Technologies
and speaks internationally to software
developers about asp.net domain driven
design design patterns solid programming
principles and how to improve quality
through refactoring Steve welcome to the
show hi thanks for having me so glad
you're here I love that your bio
mentions quality as something that
you're passionate about which is exactly
what we're here to talk about today and
so from a high level we're going to talk
about how quality relates to design to
testing to culture and other key aspects
of that concept but I want to start with
asking you why does software quality
matter and how did you come to care
about it I started caring about software
quality because I I wanted my software
to be correct I wanted it to work and
not have too many bugs and early on in
my career I was building a product and
it was an ad server because we had an
advertising network of developer
websites and I wanted it to work right I
wanted to serve the ads properly and not
crash and not slow down everybody else's
websites and so the idea that if there
was anything I could do to make it so
that it was right the first time and I
didn't have to go rebuild it or revisit
it was very important to me and you know
we'll talk about this in a moment I'm
sure but one of the things that I
realized very early on is that if you
can automate the quality checks you know
writing automated tests that's going to
get cheaper and cheaper because of Mo's
law over time versus if you have to have
manual testing that's going to get more
and more expensive because developers
and even QA Personnel tend to be you
know more and more expensive over time
so it just made sense you know as a
business owner for us to focus on that
type of building quality in approach
absolutely so so why do you think some
people sometimes may be resistant to
Quality related practices I think mostly
it's the idea that you can go fast and
the whole like move fast break things
right thing from the West Coast I think
has t to do with some of that like if
you move fast and just make a mess then
eventually that's going to come back to
haunt you right this whole technical
debt metaphor we could talk about where
you've left this big mess and it's
either going to get in your way or
you're going to have to spend even more
time cleaning it up because it's such a
mess then it would have taken to just
kind of clean things up as you go and
there's you know imagine that instead of
building software you're like running a
kitchen or running a machine shop like
if you just left a mess everywhere it
would make it much more difficult for
you to serve a quality product and that
happens in our industry too absolutely
so where does quality start in the
software development life cycle in your
experience I think it's important to
have a really good idea of what you're
building something I like to say is that
as software developers we fail in two
ways either we build the thing wrong or
we build the wrong thing and building
the wrong thing is incredibly common and
generally more expensive of a mistake
than just you know implementing
something incorrectly absolutely but as
far as where it begins I mean you know
are we talking about when you start
coding are we talking about when you
start you know putting issues in a
backlog or you talking about like where
does quality actually should it be
entering into the minds of people who
are building software yeah so to make
sure that you're building the right
thing I'm thinking it goes to even
before you enter things in the backlog
it's this conversation about what is the
overall product that we're trying to
build what is the problem that we're
solving for users lead with that make
sure the developers understand that this
is why you're building this this is the
problem it's solving many times
developers don't have that connection
they never talk to an end user they
don't even have any idea of how this
thing is used and there's plenty of
stories about developers that build
things that work great for them but
don't necessarily work for their users
like you know they're maybe they're
building a web application and they've
got got a huge desktop Monitor and it
works great there but you know most of
their users are on their phone and it
you know the developer never tests it on
a phone things like that where you
really want to understand how it's going
to be used and the problem it's going to
solve even before you think about how to
write the code for it do you have some
examples you can share maybe one example
where you've seen a lack of attention to
Quality that's negatively impacted the
ability to deliver some systems I see
this pattern a lot with clients of my my
company Nimble Pros because this is one
of the things we focus on is helping
customers that are in this position
where some Founders build a system
either they're selftaught developers or
a lot of times they've outsourced
development to often times offshore
teams that are able to quickly build
software and for the first year or two
or even three they're cranking out code
and they're getting new features and you
know they're starting to get some
customers and they're starting to grow
and by year four they notice that
everything is slowing down and they're
in fir fighter mode all the time and at
first they attribute it to oh we grew
too fast we have too many customers you
know maybe we need to you know focus
more on devops or infrastructure or
things like that but even after
attending to that you know in many cases
and I have a few customers like this
right now things just get so slow that
they can't ship new features and the
reason is that the developers went super
fast but the reason why they were fast
is because it was copy paste copy paste
copy paste oh we need another feature
copy paste that one we had oh it needs
to be a little different well just
change this one a little bit and we
don't introduce any commonality or way
to do in a single way right we don't
follow any of the you know principles
like separation of concerns or the dry
principle which you know don't use that
religiously but there are times when it
makes sense not to repeat yourself and
so you end up with systems where like
hey we need to change how sales tax
works but we've implemented purchasing
stuff in literally 10 different places
in this website and they're all like
huge complicated messes that are almost
the same but not quite and so now just
that simple thing of changing how sales
tax Works becomes like a three-month
project where it would have been an hour
in the first year of the systems
development so that that's super common
but Steve someone in a suit will say we
never would have gotten to year four if
we had thought about these things in
year 1 I think that's myopic myopic I'm
not sure yeah I agree but I'm just
saying what somebody will probably say
right so how do you respond to that
there's a mantra that if you go slow it
helps you go fast right so like moving
deliberately instead of rushing around
is the better way to have consistent
progress one of the things that tests
will do is keep from going down rabbit
holes trying to chase bugs that you
didn't even know you created in parts of
the system that you didn't think you
were affecting you know catching those
regressions very quickly and it doesn't
take long for that to pay for itself
right and so if you work on building
quality in early on it's like having a
ratchet on a strap or as you're climbing
right every so often you're climbing up
a mountain or a rock wall and you tie
into that new spot so that if you fall
you only fall down to that spot you
don't fall all the way to the bottom
right and so does that take you more
time than just free climbing the wall
yes but does it you know make it so
you're much less likely to die as a
result yes so these are the things where
it's a risk reward calculation and sure
some startup Founders might say you know
we don't need that because we just want
to get market share and prove that we
have a market and there's something to
that but if you have developers that
have the skill to build software with
tests or with quality I believe and I've
seen it that they can go just as fast or
even faster writing high quality
software than they could you know just
crank out some stuff that they consider
themselves to be low quality yeah and
that speaks to culture which we'll get
to in a little bit I believe because
when you start talking about the kinds
of developers you have and what their
capabilities are that's obviously going
to have an impact on how much you can
deliver quality software yeah definitely
before we get to that let's shift gears
a little bit and let's talk about design
which is something we mentioned you know
before we started recording is you know
designning for quality is something that
people have to consider so maybe speak a
little bit to what that means in your
experience
and then let's talk a little bit about
how principles of good design improve
software quality and maybe what some of
those principles are in your experience
sure there's whole books on principles
for Quality one of the ones that I use a
lot is separation of concerns and that
can mean different things like it's kind
of vague what are concerns but in many
cases it's technical concerns like you
want the UI and say persistence to not
be coupled to your business logic in a
lot of Legacy applications one of the
ways that teams might go faster is just
put all a whole bunch of logic in store
procedures because they're easy to
change and you can even change them at
runtime and you don't have to worry
about that pesky Source control thing in
many cases right but that eventually can
come back to bite you so you know
keeping business logic out of the
database will allow you to more easily
you know switch up databases and there's
plenty of folks that'll be saying ah
that never happens we never change our
production database well sure but you
might want to change your database in
different environments right when I run
it on Local Host maybe I just want to
spin up a cheap you know sqlite database
or something and when I run it a staging
environment something else in production
something else and so you know having
that flexibility makes it so you unlock
a lot of different ways that you could
run the application you know in
different containers or different
scenarios in your build pipeline Etc
different regions yeah yeah in different
regions separ concerns is huge and then
the other flip side of that you know if
you think about a lot of developers when
they think about the structure of a
system you think about these horizontal
layers you know if you visualize like a
a user interface layer on top and then
it talks to like a business layer of
sorts and then some kind of data access
layer right well then the other side of
that is these vertical slices where a
feature is you know a vertical slice
through that whole thing keeping those
as separate concerns also from one
another and organizing your code so that
you know pretty much all the things you
need for a given feature are organized
in a way that they're easy to find and
located near to one another helps as
well the solid principles I think are
often a good guide things like you know
classes not being too big so having only
one respons responsibility the open
close principle so that you can change
the behavior of something but I haven't
actually changed the code that leads to
a practice that I really like to share
with developers which is when you're
working on big maintainable Legacy
systems or unmaintainable Legacy systems
right one of the ways that you can make
them more maintainable is to only add
new classes with new code in them don't
go in and change a you know thousand
line long method and make it 1100 Lines
by adding another conditional to it
create a new class that has the new
condition in it and instantiate that and
call it maybe from that thousand line
long method but now you're not making
the problem worse right now you're
you're starting to make it so that
things are are smaller and more you know
easy to follow and that new class maybe
that one's unit testable even if that
other big method wasn't and so you know
open close principle is about that it's
about you know being able to create new
implementations of things rather than
having to do surgery on stuff that's
already there and then the dependency
inversion principle is huge as a way to
keep your code from being too tightly
coupled to its infrastructure code
that's tightly coupled infrastructure is
often extremely difficult or impossible
to unit test and so you have to resort
to integration tests or manual tests
which are way slower and and you know
way more expensive so yes you still want
to do some of that for sure but if you
can unit test all your business logic
without having to rely on infrastructure
you'll go a lot faster and you'll have a
lot more confidence that your business
logic works correctly absolutely I call
that separating infrastructure from
implementation which I think is what
you're saying yep for sure and then you
can test your business logic directly
and get a lot of value out of that and
to your point you do want to test the
infrastructure and do full integration
tests but if that's all you have you're
going to have some issues right yeah any
other principles of good design that's
so far you've mentioned separation of
concerns talk about solid principles you
know anything else you've seen your
experience that are principles that have
improved software quality don't repeat
yourself which I mentioned earlier the
dry principle which is very similar to
once and only once which is a older you
know extreme programming principle but
the idea that things that should have
only one rule or one you know setting in
your system should only live in one
place should only exist in one place so
that you know if you need to change it
you only have to change it in one place
you never have to go change like oh I
made this change to something now I have
to go touch 20 different files like that
change the fact that you're having to go
do shotgun surgery on your system and
change it in 20 places is telling you
that hey you you really should have just
put this in one place and had those
other ones all you know reference it
somehow and that reminds me of new as
glue which is a blog post I wrote a long
time ago but the idea that in your code
you're newing up some dependency you as
a developer every time you do that say
in your head new is glue because you're
gluing your class to that specific
implementation of that other class and
so much of the time that's not really
what you want you want to be Loosely
coupled to that thing and if you use
dependency injection or some other
technique right then you can keep that
coupling looser and not glue your code
to that other code so I I definitely use
that one a lot as well I will point out
that you can't just you know dry all the
things because every time you do remove
duplication you introduce coupling you
know you had these 20 different things
all had a copy of the same code at that
moment they were all not coupled to each
other they could all evolve
independently and maybe they should
maybe you know that's the situation
where they should all be separate from
one another and if you make them all the
same you you introduce a method that
they all call now right then the
challenge might be that you know a week
later one of them needs to change and
since you collapsed it all into one
method how are you going to do that well
we'll add a flag to the method and say
well if it's this case you know do this
other thing and now you got this tightly
coupled method everything calls it
starts to become this complex you know
mess of if logic like no take the one
that needs to be separate and distinct
and don't have it called the method
anymore right and just have the special
you know code that it does be in that
one place not you know commonly with all
the other ones yeah so a couple things
have come up here which I think are even
more abstract in some of those design
principles but I think they're a good
starting point you've mentioned coupling
is one and I think sort of inherently
cohesion has also come out of that as
well and also to do a lot of what you're
describing requires people to consider
encapsulation so let's talk about those
a little bit and how they relate to
Quality coupling cohesion and
encapsulation what happens to your
software when you don't consider those
things and what impact does that have on
quality and when you do consider them
why does it improve quality sure so a
really good book for coupling and
cohesion that's kind of a classic at
this point is Steve McConnell's code
complete from back in the 90s so I'd
recommend that for folks that haven't
read it coupling refers to how things
call one another right how reference one
another and you can have loose coupling
or tight coupling and your system is
going to have coupling right it has to
if it's going to do anything useful and
so it's not a matter of like coupling is
bad it's like you want to make conscious
decisions about where it makes sense for
you to have tight coupling to certain
things and you know loose coupling to
others to the extent that you can you
want to have your system be Loosely
coupled to the infrastructure and the
environment in which it finds itself
running right 20 years ago we weren't
anticipating you know Docker containers
as a thing but now they're common right
so having that ability to ship around
executables in a stable environment
using containers is an example of
something where having Loosely coupled
code makes it really easy for you to
swap out you know different
infrastructure just as a different
Docker container but only if your code
is written in a way that it could talk
to something else right and if your code
is hard-coded to always talk to let's
say a local SQL database then it's going
to be really difficult for you to change
that up so using abstractions as a way
to make your coupling looser and say I
depend on a contract I depend on an
interface or an abstraction I don't
depend on the implementation that can be
swapped out at runtime makes your code
much more flexible and kind of future
proof now you could also argue that yagy
comes into play there like you don't
want to overly abstract things but for
basic stuff like what's the UI concerns
what's the data concerns having that
minimal level of abstraction I have
found to be extremely valuable now
cohesion is kind of related to coupling
but cohesion is basically how related
are the things within some module or
some class right so if we're talking
like object-oriented programming you've
got a class it's got a bunch of fields
and a bunch of methods if it has you
know three fields that are used by two
methods and a couple other fields that
are used by a different other couple of
methods then it's almost like you have
two classes inside of one struggling to
break apart because they're not cohesive
right and so if you can split those up
it'll usually lead to a better design I
work a lot with C andn Net and for the
last 15 years they've been mostly doing
MVC model view controller patterns for
their web Frameworks and it's super
common and I know this is true in other
languages that use these patterns as
well for controllers to be super large
super wide you bled and that's a
cohesion problem right like you'll go
into a controller it's got like 10
different action methods and you look at
the Constructor for all the dependencies
and it's got like 30 dependencies that
are injected you look at any one action
method it's using three four maybe five
of them but it's not cohesive at all and
you're ended up having to inject all
these things even for Action methods
that don't need most of it so splitting
those up into end points is definitely
something that I do to try and make
things more cohesive more single
responsibility those two kind of go hand
inand single responsibility principle
and cohesion and then what was the third
encapsulation encapsulation what's that
oh encapsulation is like one of my
favorite topics and the idea with
encapsulation is simply that you don't
know how the sausage is made on the
other side of a call right and so it's
information hiding and the
implementation details are not something
you know or care about about and by
leveraging encapsulation it makes it so
our designs are much better it's
necessary for any kind of modularity
right we wouldn't be able to use plugs
into the wall for electricity without
encapsulation of you know everybody can
design a cord that's a certain thickness
and has prongs in a certain orientation
and if they do they can plug into this
interface and get you know power at a
way that works for them and they don't
have to worry about well am I talking to
solar power am I talking to a generator
am I talking to the grid am I talking to
a battery like doesn't matter as long as
it's you know AC or DC or whatever that
needs and you know certain specs of that
power it's happy and it'll work our code
operates under these same assumptions so
if you can code to an interface a
specification that says what you need
and and how you need it and not exactly
how it's done your code is going to be
more modular which makes it more
maintainable in my experience there's
two hard problems in software
engineering their information hiding and
dependency management and I think that's
kind of where we've landed here because
a lot of those design patterns have to
do with how you manage your dependencies
you know you mentioned dependency
inversion things like that and like that
design pattern and then information
hiding I really appreciate that you
connected encapsulation with information
hiding because a lot of people I don't
think know that they are connected and
I'll Point our listeners to the 1972
paper by David paros called on the
criteria to be used in decomposing
systems into modules and for 52 years
we've had the answer to how to hide
information properly within systems but
so many people are unaware of how to do
it so I'd really encourage people to
spend more time looking into that but
for the purposes of this conversation
Steve speak a little bit to kind of
wrapping those back into how do cohesion
coupling encapsulation relate to Quality
in case that's not really clear to
listeners at this point yeah I think one
of the things that helps to demonstrate
quality is to know that your code does
what it's supposed to do right now how
do you know that your code does what
it's supposed to well you run it and you
go through the application and it looks
like it's supposed to look right but
that takes a lot of time and if you're
having to do that over and over and over
again like that's eating up your
productivity so if there were a way to
automate that then you could know and
have confidence that your code does what
it's supposed to do and it's not enough
to know that it does what it's supposed
to do once right every time you make a
change you want to still know that it
still does what it was supposed to do so
you know the short answer is like having
some automated Suite of tests gives you
confidence that your code still does
what it's supposed to do could the test
be wrong yes could you know other things
go wrong with that yeah it's not
infallible but but in general having
those unit tests gives you this check
and in a fast cheap way to know that
things are working the way they were
supposed to at the time that you wrote
those tests and so that's huge I have
also found that there's a huge overlap
between the ven diagrams of unit
testable code and what I consider to be
highquality Loosely coupled code they're
almost the same Circle right and so if
you maybe don't have time to write unit
tests for whatever reason or you know
this particular code is not something
that you're too worried about out you
know you're just going to knock it out
and you only have to have 100% test
coverage that's fine but if you still
write it in a unit testable way then
it's still going to be high quality code
in terms of being easy to test easy to
change you know not tightly coupled to
infrastructure Etc and so later on if it
becomes more complex and you find
yourself scratching your head about well
why isn't this working I thought this
was simple now you could write a couple
tests and prove out you know what it's
doing I find that writing tests is the
best way for me to understand what my
code is doing and you know there was a
conversation I had a few months ago on
Twitter about you know folks that use
the debugger all day long versus folks
that almost never do I I very rarely use
the debugger usually it's I'm debugging
a test to figure out like why is this
test not doing what I expect but because
I have all these tests I know what the
code does I don't have to debug through
it to figure it out Legacy code from a
new client that I've never seen before
yes I'll use a debugger to kind of Step
through and see what's going on but for
code that I've been writing and I've got
a bunch of tests for I find I don't need
to jump into the debugger nearly as
often so to summarize that what I think
you're saying in general is testable
code tends to have loose coupling High
cohesion and good encapsulation yes it
doesn't necessarily have to have good
encapsulation but yes tends to tends to
Sure tends to and knowing what the
interfaces are between things can make
things more testable as well because
you're now depending on abstractions
instead of concrete implementations
which hearkens back to the design
patterns we were speaking to before
that's right so you talked about Legacy
systems and I do want to shift gears and
talk a little bit more about testing and
quality assurance but let's start there
let's start with a lot of our listeners
are dealing with Brownfield systems and
you know maybe they've heard of the
Strangler fig pattern and things like
this you know that Martin fer talks
about in his website and I'm sure others
have have spoken to as well but where do
you start with introducing quality
practices into an environment where
maybe those have been lacking well I
would start with Source control right
Believe It or Not There are some clients
out there that aren't using Source
control you know some companies and
teams and occasionally they come
knocking on our door so the first thing
we do is we get them on GitHub using GS
if possible because that's our best
recommendation for that and have some
Source control like now you've got
Source control that's table Stakes
that's great next step is you want to
make sure that stuff works on someone
else's machine besides yours and the
easiest way to do that is to set up a
GitHub action or an Azure devops you
know whatever they're called pipeline or
team City or whatever you want to use
for your CI server and build the thing
on another machine right that tells you
that you know this thing isn't dependent
on some setting and your registry or
some you know dependency that only you
have installed and goes a long way
toward making sure you you don't have
the works on my machine syndrome that a
lot of times you run into once you have
that and your initial CI script is just
build the code then you add build the
code and run the tests right and ideally
the most important tests to run are your
unit tests because they're going to be
the easiest ones to put in your build
pipeline because they don't have any
dependencies on anything so you don't
have to say oh well I would put that in
the build pipeline but I need a database
and I need a web server and I need this
and I need that like no it's just run
your unit tests against your package of
your code that's it and that should be
super trivial to do in your build server
and maybe initially you don't have any
tests that's fine now that you have the
infrastructure in place where your tests
matter right I wouldn't lead with tests
and the reason is if one developer
decides they're going to write tests and
nobody else is bought in and it doesn't
have anything to do with their build
release cycle then those tests are going
to break from time to time and no one's
going to care except for that one
developer and they might yell and say
hey you broke the test like nobody cares
it's not there problem you wanted to
write those tests you go fix them
whereas if you put it as part of the
continuous integration script that is
used you know as a gate before your code
deploys to the next environment now when
tests are broken everybody cares right
you got to fix that or else the script
isn't going to you know publish your
code to the next step and so once you
have that in place now testing becomes
important to the whole team and everyone
can start to get bought into the value
of them unless they go and they comment
out the tests but that's that does
happen some we get to culture we'll talk
about that and that's unfortunate but it
does happen so a little bit more though
about I've got a legacy system and I
don't have any unit tests and we want to
start testing the system like what would
you do to start validating the at least
current behavior of the system so you
could start with confidence introducing
you know some of these changes in
patterns and and in testing right well
there's this idea of a testing pyramid
where you have like manual tests and
user interface tests and an integration
test and then unit test and the reason
it's shaped like that is that you
generally want to have more of the
things at the base of the pyramid which
in this case is unit test and fewer of
the UI and manual tests it may be in a
legacy system that is not very unit
testable and so you may have they only
have like manual testers and that's it
maybe they're using you know playr or
some other thing to automate some UI
tests right take whatever automated
tests you can find or quickly write and
put those into the build process as soon
as you can and then you will almost
certainly be able to find some places
where you can do unit tests right pure
functions that just rely on their inputs
and give you some output as a result are
always unit testable and there's usually
a way that you can find some places in
the code where you can extract something
out and turn it into a pure function
right maybe it's that if statement
that's like seven lines long and tests a
bunch of different random things like
take that if statement put it into a
pure function that says you know if some
good name for what that condition really
means and put all that other logic in it
and now you can write a whole bunch of
unit tests that say Hey if I have this
and that and the other it should be true
and if I have that and the other it
should be false right those are your
first unit test they like pick the easy
things that you can pull out and then
you just kind of grow from there you
want to refactor and we haven't talked
about refactoring yet but you want to
refactor that Legacy system to make it
easier over time to test and ideally
when you're refactoring you want to have
some tests and initially that might just
be manual tests or you know UI tests but
as you progress you know you'll start to
have a larger and larger Suite of unit
tests that are helping you and the thing
to remind yourself or the client or the
team is that you didn't get here in a
day right usually you have you know many
developer years of effort when into
building this Legacy system with no you
know idea about tests or code quality
even necessarily right and so now we're
going to start to turn the ship but it's
a big ship and it's not going to turn
quickly right or for another metaphor
like if you have neglected your health
for you know 20 years and now you're
overweight and not as fit as you would
like and you decide to go to the gym
like a week later you're still going to
be pretty much how the last 20 years
have put you right it's going to take
some time to change the direction there
and it's the same for your codebase if
your codebase is unfit it's going to
take a while for good habits to move it
back into a fit course yeah I will point
out for people just getting started too
one of the things I'll often recommend
is especially now with a lot of the
advanced cicd and things that you can do
even with GitHub actions you can spin up
Docker containers to do some of those
infrastructural pieces that you need in
order for some you know large scale
infrastructure tests to run and so I
just encourage people don't run away
from making a Legacy system testable
even if it's integration testing while
you need to have a larger quantity of
more focused unit oriented tests you
should still also be able to test the
whole system and there are ways to do
that so definitely want to encourage
people to still do that if they want to
improve the quality of a legacy system
yep I agree definitely being able to put
a database in a container and spin that
up as part of the cicd process is great
it's amazing you can get Rabbid mq
running in those if you want to test
your you know maybe using mass transit
or something like that for a message bus
you know there's all kinds of things you
can do now with Docker that were a lot
more challenging to do you know even
just 10 years ago definitely 15 years
ago yeah one thing I I'll point out on
that before we move on is separate your
tests into different projects if you can
or have a way to run different kinds of
tests at different times I usually will
separate unit tests and integration
tests at a minimum mostly because of
speed I can run unit tests I know in any
environment whether it's locally or in a
pipeline and they should all run in
seconds whereas if we are talking about
standing Docker containers in a GitHub
action or in a pipeline a lot of times
it's going to have to pull in that
Docker container and that's going to
take time not the mention even just
running the test and then resetting the
state of that infrastructure so those
integration tests will probably take
minutes not seconds and so you're not
going to want to run those in the same
scenarios necessarily right you know if
your test Suite always takes 12 hours to
run yeah right it's not as useful as a
test Suite that takes five or 10 minutes
to run and so you want to be able to at
least split those out so that you get
the fast feedback from the unit test and
then in a pipeline somewhere that maybe
takes 10 or 20 or a half an hour right
you get the full Suite of integration
and functional tests absolutely and you
know multiple ways to do that right you
mentioned different projects you can
also with attributes you know you can
just like segment and say these are
integration some way to be able to run
them separately that's right that's
right but again and and doing both but
that ability to have the quick feedback
is absolutely super helpful for teams
and I think for legacy teams who start
to have that experience too it can
become addictive in a good way like in a
healthy you know
a good feedback loop you can with
certain tools like I typically use
Visual Studio but there's there's other
tools you can do it from the command
line in theet ecosystem where you can
just have the test run continuously
right so there's live unit testing is a
feature in in the IDE but even at the
command line you can say net watch test
and it will just every time you change a
file it reruns all the tests so you know
even if you're using vs code on a Mac
and don't pay Microsoft anything like
you've got you know this this feature
where you can be seeing your unit tests
running continuously as you save one
line of code that's right well I use vs
code on a Mac but it doesn't prevent me
from giving Microsoft money for other
reasons but that's a whole another topic
of conversation so let's switch gears a
little bit to dive a little bit deeper
into testing and how it relates to
quality assurance and to kick that off
first question are there any
misconceptions that people have about
testing um I think there's maybe the
just misconception that it's it's really
hard or if you don't have it it's it's
hard to get started like if you're the
developer on the team that wants to try
it that it's this big uphill journey to
try and get Buy in from everybody to you
know add a class that runs some tests
like it's it's not a big deal and you
can start it on just your machine and
see how it's useful to you don't even
check it in right just just keep it
locally and then when you you know at
some point you've got a bunch of them
and you can show everybody else how
great they are you know then you can
kind of reduce the fear or or the
concern about how big they are because
for folks who have never done it it may
seem like this scary thing right just
because it's not in their comfort zone
so you know being willing to just step
in and try it I think is huge the other
thing that I find is a good way to get
teams to start using tests that aren't
used to it and kind of change that
culture is for bug fixing right so if
you have a rule that says bugs are not
closed out as fixed unless there's a
test showing that that bug no longer
exists then if that's the only time you
ever write tests your code is going to
start to get much better quickly because
guess what all the places in your code
that are most error prone are going to
be the ones that have the most tests in
in a very short while and that's going
to force you to refactor that code to be
looking at code trying to improve it and
of course adding tests to it to make
sure that the next change you make
doesn't break and introduce a regression
that you already fixed last month
because now you've got a bug fixed test
in place yeah that's the aha moment for
me when I first started testing years
ago was when we found and we started
doing exactly what you said it was okay
if a bug is found the first thing you
have to do is actually you have to have
a test that fails that proves the bug
exists yes once you have that then you
have to change the code to get the test
to go from red to green and the real aha
moment was when one of us on our team
did that and something else that had
been green turned red and we went uh and
we caught it yeah and it was fantastic
because now we weren't playing
whack-a-mole and having a customer tell
us hey you fixed that but you broke this
which is the worst y it's a morale
killer all your tests just paid for
themselves in that moment they did and
this was years ago and it was when we
were just getting started but it was
fantastic just to have that the whole
team went ah like okay it's like yes now
I get it this is why people talk about
this this is why we do this well and
it's funny too because it's how the real
world works I mean you know you don't
build an automobile and just crash test
it right yeah you tested every component
was tested and you testing materials and
you like going all the way back up the
supply chain you're testing every aspect
of the supply chain so that when you put
the car together and I think this is
something that you've probably realized
too is Crash testing the car is not
quality assurance that's quality control
sure yeah well testing your UI when
you've already built the product is not
quality assurance that's quality
control and quality control is important
but it only tells you that you missed
some serious problems you need to go
back and fix but it doesn't fix any
problems right best it detects them yeah
and that's another misconception I think
people have how about this one what are
your thoughts on code coverage like
we're going for 100% on everything like
is that for a lot of Legacy systems I
like to just see code coverage going up
okay yeah and that's what the team you
know maybe gets some additional
confidence around and for really big
systems right it's going to start out at
like 0 one% you added like one test
right and then over time it starts to to
grow I am not concerned about 100% code
coverage I want to test the parts the
code that are important if they aren't
working and almost always that means
writing tests for things that have
conditional logic in them so a key
metric that I use is cyclomatic
complexity measures but only on the on
the method level if you try and apply it
at class or or higher level it doesn't
it doesn't make any sense but at the
method level if you can keep cyclomatic
complexity down like under 10 and for
folks that don't know that that you know
there's a good definition on Wikipedia
But essentially it's like how many
different ways can logic flow through
this method and so if you have an if
statement that says you know it's either
this or it's that then you have two ways
right it's going to hit one side or the
other of that if statement and many
times we'll find in Legacy code you know
cyclomatic complexity of some of the the
most important parts of the system in
the hundreds for a method and that's
just insane right because you really
want to have a test for every one of
those cases so you would need like
hundreds of tests for that method to to
fully you know exercise it and you you
could get to 100% code coverage on that
method way before you covered all the
different combinations of paths that
might lead through it so keeping that
low pays big dividends so that that's
pretty much where I try and focus is not
so much on a particular percentage more
is usually better but but only if it's
you know interesting code that you care
if it fails or or that it could fail
right I don't test properties like in do
net C code we have properties as a
built-in feature they work right the the
language team proved that they worked so
I don't have to write it that's already
been tested every single property right
that's that's not necessary no that's
interesting he correlated that too with
conditional logic because that that
makes a lot of sense that's where you're
going to you know find those edge cases
or things like that and and that's where
it might make sense to say we're going
to aim for 100% coverage on this
conditional thing maybe before we start
refactoring it and trying to fix it sure
because we want to have confidence as we
refactor that we're at least not
regressing and making things worse than
they were when we found them for
example even things that aren't
properties that just have only one code
path through it like you you extracted
out a method that does four things and
and it's just some you know helper
method that has no if statements in it
like you know it does those four things
like you know there there's no other way
it could possibly go so you don't
necessarily have to test that method you
probably test the method that calls it
but you know you don't NE necessarily
have to test that separate method yeah
that actually goes back to you know
another design principle we didn't
mention before but command query
separation from I think it's from
Bertrand Russell the idea that a method
should either change state or report on
state but not do both at the same time
and that's another one of those
principles that you know people can
consider when they're trying to make
their systems more testable for example
because if I know this method's going to
change State then I'm testing to State
change and I if it's only going to
report on state then I'm just testing
that you know it's in the appr expect or
what yeah exactly exactly so that can
help as well any other misconceptions
maybe people have we've covered a few
but a lot of folks get hung up on
mocking and you know some folks think
that the only reason that you would ever
have an interface in your in your code
or an abstraction is because it you to
mock things for your test and sometimes
that's useful but that's not the primary
benefit or reason I think too many folks
kind of go down the rabbit hole with
mocking and I look at their tests and
like one test method is like 50 lines
long and the first 40 are setting up all
the mocks like you know that's
indicative that you have a problem with
your code that you're trying to test and
it's like way too coupled to a whole
bunch of of dependencies and things so
if you can refactor the code so it
doesn't need that and IDE try and use as
many pure functions as possible so
because those are easy to test you know
you're going to have a a much easier
time with testing so you know don't be
afraid to mock a couple things here and
there if it makes it easier to make a
test for something but if you find that
you're spending an inordinate amount of
time trying to deal with and set up
mocks that's a smell that's telling you
your design could be improved Yeah you
mentioned before like a controller that
might have 13 dependencies injected into
it or something like that and then if
you are trying to test that controller
and you have to mock out all 13 of those
things or to your other point if you're
only testing one method on it but it
only needs two of those 13 things and
you only those two something's telling
you that maybe you should refine Your
Design as opposed to just continuing to
go down this path of you know
complicated mock setups and and things
of that nature right another common
thing I see especially for folks new to
testing is they don't treat the test
code like real code in terms of trying
to refactor it and keep it clean and
maintainable so really common one is
just the new keyword again you know I
talk about new is glue like if you have
the new keyword neing up the system
under test in you know every single test
for a certain class and you know later
on this big you know very important
class has 50 different unit tests and
every single one of them instantiates it
and then you're like oh we need this
dependency add it to the Constructor
great now you've got 50 tests you have
to go fix because every one of them says
oh I don't have a Constructor that has
that thing don't do that right there
should be like one place in in your test
Suite where you instantiate the system
under test and then all the other tests
you know use that and just by doing that
one simple thing now when you make
changes to the system under test it's
less painful it's less friction you're
not going to be resentful of having to
make a change because oh now I have to
go fix all the tests right like no make
your job easier make it so you only have
to fix that one place where you
instantiate that class and not every
place that you have a test for it yeah
we had Chad Michelle on the show a
couple months ago and he wrote a book
called lean software systems engineering
for developers it's a mouthful but one
of the concepts from the book I really
appreciate how they put it they call it
design for change yeah and I think
that's exactly what we're all trying to
do and we're trying to avoid that pain
as we should you know sometimes change
are painful but we can make them less
painful and when we designed for change
then it just makes everybody's lives
better right yeah so let's talk about
testing best practices so what does a
robust testing strategy look like in
your experience for a software
development team one of the things
speaking of teams and I know we'll get
to culture here in a little bit but
something I often find as a problem in
teams is that they have a separate QA
team from the developers and almost
always I find it's better if we're able
to integrate those and have you know QA
on the team with the developers you know
building the test as part of the
iteration or Sprint and working side by
side with developers on automating tests
and other things there's that first off
if you've got a separate QA team that's
only a hindrance in my experience
assuming that you've you know got folks
that are invested in quality and in
writing tests on the team then the way I
would approach it for legacy code is to
start with some you know tests that are
probably high level and you know do like
playright tests or or UI bu tests that
prove the most important things work
maybe these are like smoke tests that
you run right before you go to
production can the user log in can they
you know add items to their cart can
they check out you know with a fake you
know credit card or whatever because
those might be the most important things
that the application does and so once
you've got some of the minimal stuff in
place to give you some confidence that
the code works then you work down from
there and like I said I'm a fan of
writing unit test for the business logic
where the most important complexity
lives and so start to write tests for
that if you can't write unit test you
know write some integration tests for
that but eventually you want to get the
code into a state where you've
refactored it to where the business
logic decisions live independent of the
infrastructure and now that unlocks the
ability for you to unit test those which
pays huge dividends when business logic
changes which it often does on these
Legacy systems it's like we want to ship
a new feature or this regulation changed
or we need to add another payment
provider we need to change how sales tax
works because we just started you know
we have a customer in Brazil now and
they have a whole different set of laws
like stuff's going to happen and if
everything is just hardcoded and coupled
together and and directly into a
database or whatever those are really
hard to do and you know the first one or
two might not be too bad you'll just add
some more if logic in there but you know
after 10 or 12 you know locations and
and strategies and different approaches
it becomes a big spaghetti code mess and
suddenly all your progress grinds to a
halt what about other kinds of testing
like performance testing and security
testing how do those relate to Quality
in your experience I think those are
important but it's a different skill set
I I think performance testing I I've
done talks and courses on performance
testing and measuring performance and
scalability with load tests and things
not all companies have the the resources
for that and a lot of times it's more of
a if the customer is telling you this
page is slow that's when we need to to
worry about that and in that case you
know before you go doing Performance
Tuning it's just like when you are going
to fix a bug you should have a test for
it you should have a test that
demonstrates that the performance isn't
satisfactory so that when you tune it
you can rerun test and say look I fixed
it right it's it's a bug that it's not
fast enough so treat it like one and
write a performance test for that and
then you'll know when you're done
because otherwise it's really hard to
say when you're done performance tuning
and developers can spend an infinite
amount of time trying to make something
a little bit faster when when really you
know you get the biggest Bang from some
lwh hanging fruit like adding caching or
adding an index and you don't have to go
and like try and tweak how every method
is called and whether or not it's on the
Heap or the stack like most of that
doesn't matter when when you're talking
over the network to a database or
distributed system security is
definitely important and there's third
party tools you can use to like scan
your code for known security issues I
would encourage every developer to keep
an eye on the oasp website the which
kind of lists like you know every two or
three years they list the top 10
security problems definitely keep an eye
on that and understand how to look for
those one of the biggest ones remains
SQL injection so you know make sure that
your site is not taking in user input
and using it to build queries against
your database that's still one of the
biggest risks out there so at least be
sure you're not introducing those into
your system but then there's also a
place for you know third party security
audits from time to time where folks
that that's all they do can come in and
take a look at your code for a week or
two and give you a laundry list of
things that you could be fixing that's
probably more effective for most
organizations than trying to have all of
their developers be up to speed on every
security exploit all the time because I
don't think that's tenable yeah and we
don't have time to get into in this
episode but I I think it does somewhat
relate to Quality we talk about
something like threat modeling and
actually considering the threat vectors
for your system and what your strategies
will be for mitigating or eliminating
those threats which again you know that
I think relates to Quality because if
your system can be hacked and and taken
over I think you've got some serious
problems there sure things that are
quality related to that too are the more
modular your system is the more places
you have where you can insert additional
functionality for instance you know
maybe initially you don't have any way
to know what an attacker did if they get
into your system because you don't have
be logging right well you can easily add
a bunch of logging in like decorators or
chain of responsibility pattern or or
behaviors instead of having to go touch
every single service and every single
controller and every method and be like
hey entered this method hey exited this
method like there's ways when you write
your code using good patterns that you
can get that type of behavior across the
board or do a security check as some
middleware across the board without
having to go do surgery on every part of
your application absolutely in fact I
forgot to mention it before but I'll
mention it now one of the first books I
learned on refactoring things to make
them more testable and that's not the
title of the book but the title of the
book was refactoring to patterns by
Joshua kvki and I'll put a link in the
show notes but for people who are
wondering how do I take that nasty IFL
switch case statement that's you know
got a cyclomatic complexity of a
thousand and start cleaning it up books
like that I think are a good place to
get started giving you some creative
ideas like you mentioned you know chain
of responsibility pattern again we'll
put a link in the show notes but just
giving people creative ideas is to think
about oh maybe there's other ways to to
reduce the complexity in this code and
make things more understandable and also
more testable which improves the quality
of the system overall let's talk about
building a quality culture so I know you
do a lot of Consulting and you help
companies to improve their development
practices so what in your experience
does it take to help build a culture of
quality in a software company I mean
that's a big topic there's there's whole
books on that there's a great book that
I would recommend that the technical
leadership in those companies read which
is accelerate which has a bunch of
scientifically proven things that you
can do that lead to better impacts uh
and outcomes for your software process
youve probably talked to people on this
show about that book in the past so I
won't get into it too much but you know
that would be a good place to start is
the practices that that are outlined in
that book and the Buy in that it's not
just voodoo magic and and some
consultant coming in because they get a
paycheck saying hey you should do this
like no this is scientifically proven
practices at this point and so getting
that buyin from leadership is usually an
important first step because it's it's
difficult to do you know change in an
organization from like the individual
developer individual contributor up the
stack but if the technical leadership
buys into this then then that can help
now the next step is how how do you get
those individual contributors on board
and that can be a challenge right a lot
of folks will be eager to learn new
things eager to write better code eager
to work on a system that's more modular
and isn't a big Tangled spaghetti code
mess other developers you know maybe
they're later in their career and
they've been working at the company for
decades and they're like you know I
don't really see a need to change I've
been doing this for 20 years and it's
always worked for me and that can be
more of a challenge so ideally you get
everybody on board and if you can't then
sometimes you reorg a little bit and you
have like you know developers that
aren't as interested in learning these
new techniques are you know put on teams
or put on code that they can be
successful in without having to if
that's possible sometimes it's just a
matter of changing your team and you
know maybe you make sure that the next
few developers you hire all have the
same mindset that you're looking for and
sometimes unfortunately you you have to
let other developers go that don't but
you know that should be a last resort
and ideally you can bring everybody
along and those developers that have
been there for a long time also have a
ton of understanding of how that Legacy
system works so you definitely don't
want to lose them just because in the
first week they don't jump up and down
to do unit tests so I think those are
like two ends of the spectrum right the
management leadership side the
individual contributor side if you can
get the team to be self-empowered to the
point where they can decide how they're
going to achieve some of these things
that can help a lot right so it's not
just dictated from on high you know the
CTO says we will now have code coverage
of 100% period or you're fired like that
doesn't change the culture and it
doesn't necessarily work great because
doesn't take long for developers to
figure out that they can write one unit
test that iterates through all the
classes in the system and you know hits
all their properties and then returns
true like hey you just you know got
almost all the code coverage with that
one test like do anything useful no but
your gameing the system and developers
are are usually pretty good at that so
it's more important that you you know
show the results that you're going for
then that you have some arbitrary metric
that may be difficult absolutely let's
pay people by lines of code yeah the
adage is and if it can be measured it
will be gained and and to your point
developers are really good at that Yep
this does make me think of a of a
concept I don't think it's in his book
but uh yval Loy who's a trainer of
software Architects he says that you
should have zero tolerance for defects
and that doesn't mean you necessarily
have zero defects because sometimes
defects up through but you Zero
Tolerance if a defect is found stop the
presses where fixing it we're going to
eradicate that defect right yep and
that's a lean principle you know stop
the line stop the line Jeffrey poo a
friend of mine I'm don't know if this
was his original quote but he he said
something that resonated with me which
is that if you have a process that
produces defects then you have a
defective process yeah I like that I
like that's very related yeah well let's
talk about pull the chord because may
maybe not everybody's familiar with what
you're talking about sure so there's a
great book by Mary papendick called lean
software development it has some some
principles but one of the key practices
that lean follows in you know
manufacturing setting is that if there's
a defect you stop the line meaning stop
the assembly line everybody stops work
and you don't just fix that one defect
you fix the thing that allowed that
defect to happen so that that defect
never happens again in software that
mean you write a unit test that says
that bug is fixed and it won't happen
again or you change the build pipeline
so that you actually run the unit test
or whatever it might be that would make
it so that that failure that you've just
discovered you don't just fix it you fix
the things that led to it being possible
and then now your process is slightly
better for the next time and if you do
that consistently you'll go faster
because you won't have to keep fighting
fires most folks that are dealing
dealing with Legacy systems have
management that's trying to go faster
and the dev team and devops team are
just trying to put out the fires as fast
as they can and they don't have time to
to even think about system quality
because they're too busy just you know
dealing with all the bugs and and
critical issues that are happening all
around them and so you want to build
that quality in so you never get to that
state where it's constant firefighting
I'll Point listeners to if you're
interested to dig deeper into this
Edward Deming who's the father of total
quality management was responsible for
the Japanese transformation of Toyota in
the 1950s you know basically took over
the world a lot of this lean and these
kinds of principles comes from something
called the andon cord which is a white
cord that anyone on the factory line
could pull even the janitor and if they
found there was no defect this is the
fascinating thing if they found there
wasn't a defect they still rewarded the
person for pulling the cord because what
they cared about and I think this is
really pertinent to our industry these
days is you know all of these different
methodologies and things we have which
we're not going to get into now because
we're talking about quality but it
really in my experience Steve and I
wonder if this gals with yours it boils
down to continuous process Improvement
whatever methodology you have or
whatever practices you have if you're
not doing CPI I'd question whether what
you're doing is really helping you or
not what are your thoughts on that yeah
I would definitely agree there's various
you know agile maturity models and
things and a lot of folks don't like the
term maturity in in in there but you
know if you look at those you can see
where organizationally and the processes
you follow there's things that are
Stepping Stones to getting better and
better right like I was saying you know
some teams don't even have Source
control right and if you don't have
Source control there there's a whole lot
of activities that you can't even start
to think about doing until you get that
in place right and then I was big early
on in our discussion about continuous
integration or CI most people just say
cic CD Now is like this you know
buzzword that I hear but very few teams
are actually doing the cd part which is
continuous delivery or continuous
deployment and to get to continuous
delivery or deployment requires a whole
additional set of capabilities in your
team and in your in your devops to be
able to support like generally you're
going to have to have support for
feature Flags you're going to have to be
good at trunk-based development and and
that's not something necessarily teams
understand or or use or or aware of on
the first day right and so this idea
that you're continuously improving your
process some of that is going to be
novel and unique to you and your team
and your org and some of it is going to
be these are well understood stepping
stones in the industry that we know that
we can get to and again I'll Point
people at the accelerate book but being
able to get to being at the point where
you can do continuous delivery where
every time someone checks something in
if it goes through all the gates and
passes all the quality checks it's live
like that is kind of like the epitome of
where you can get with your your
software process absolutely and I think
that's the idea of the continuous it's
like wherever you're at right now you're
continually improving your process and
then of course there's metrics and
tracking and things like that that all
matter do you have any specific example
of a team or someone you were you don't
have to say who of course but you know
where the improvements in quality had
such a market impact that it was just
like amazing sure this is kind of
working at it from the other end so and
I like I like to tell this story for
folks one of the things that I think
helps a lot is shipping more often right
we just talked about CD continuous
delivery I think that's crucial but even
if you can't get to that at least doing
it more frequently can almost certainly
help there's a a principal or quote that
I'm not sure where it's from it's if it
hurts do it more often right if if your
process of shipping software right now
is painful it will get less painful if
you do it more often so I had a client a
few years ago they would ship software
whenever the product manager felt like
it was worth shipping right if it had
enough features in it that you know
users would benefit from it then we it's
fine we'll schedule a release and so
this worked out to be about every six or
eight weeks and every time they they did
this their software was used you know
seven days a week during business hours
so they would have to deploy at 3:00 in
the morning on a Tuesday and you know
make sure that you know hopefully it
worked almost never did right so there'd
be several attempts to deploy between
3:00 a.m. and 5:00 a.m. and usually by
8:00 a.m. they could get the thing
working enough and they might still have
a few little minor things they'd fix
like the next day on Wednesday they
might get you know at 6:00 a.m. and and
do a couple more little tweaks and so I
was trying to convince them that you
should really be deploying more often
right well the developer Team all of
whom had to get up once every couple of
months at 3 o'clock in the morning and
their families who didn't really
appreciate that either they didn't
really want to hear from me that hey we
should do this more often but what I
started them to do is for about six
months they would record every time they
deployed and when that happened and
whether or not it was successful right
and it was successful if you didn't have
to roll it back and you didn't have to
immediately you know fix some bug that
you discovered in production right and
then relate that to how long had it been
since the last deployment right and very
quickly you look at the data it says if
it's been more than an hour since the
last deployment you know it's never
successful right or you know maybe a day
right more if it's been more than a day
it's never successful but if it's been
less than a day it's almost always
successful and so what we got them to do
is start shipping you know ship again on
Thursday right not much has happened
it's still about the same code that it
was okay now ship again on Tuesday right
and so they started shipping every
Tuesday and Thursday and they found that
it wasn't that hard it didn't take that
long if something was broken they knew
exactly what it was cuz they just did it
and you know now they're shipping over
100 times a year they don't necessarily
feel like they need to get beyond that
like that's working for them but it's
it's made a huge difference in the
quality and the speed with which they're
able to move because they aren't
spending so much time trying to figure
this out and now they they deploy
lunchtime right it's not a big deal so
no one's getting up at 3 o' in the
morning and and it's been a a huge
quality of life Improvement for the
development teams as well yeah I
remember that transition in one of my
companies years ago as well where
everybody was afraid to deploy on
Fridays right and so we switched the
narrative and we said we're always going
to deploy on Friday no matter what and
it only took a few months and next thing
you know there were never any weekend
interruptions anymore right and nobody
was afraid to De play on Friday anymore
because of all the things you just
described when you have those quality
practices those Gates those tests those
you know everything in place and
suddenly you're like oh yeah this is no
big deal we do this all the time and
it's it's do it more often it'll force
you to improve it if you only do it once
in a blue moon it's not worth it to fix
it because you only do it once in the
blue moon but if you're doing it every
week or a couple times a week like well
we better get better at this we better
be more
that's right and when you've only
changed three things instead of 300 it's
you know more likely you're going to be
able to figure out what went wrong and
fix it quickly instead of you know
combing through and finding a needle in
a in a hay stack and I think as we wrap
things up that kind of speaks back to
culture as well you know what kind of
company do you want to work for do you
want to work with one that's afraid to
make changes and anytime they do
everything breaks and you're staying up
late at night and that creates stress
and that leads to all kinds of problems
you know at the extreme end it literally
leads to ends of relationships and ends
of lives and so you know so quality
matters quality matters and working on a
code base where you know everything is
modular there's tests for things you're
able to check stuff in and all the tests
pass and the code just goes through like
there's no stress right there's minimal
stress things don't fail that often is a
night and day difference versus you know
Legacy code no tests lots and lots of
manual testing lots and lots of cross
your fingers and pray whenever you do a
deployment it's way more stressful in
that environment than in the one that I
would prefer to work in absolutely so as
we wrap things up if people want to find
out more about what you're up to or
maybe even ask you some more questions
or get your help in improving their
quality practices in their company where
should they go sure so you can find me
online as our Dallas just about
everywhere that's spelled a r d a l i
and so because my name is Steve Smith
it's really hard to get a username that
has any combination of that with
consistency so I've been our Dallas
online for over 20 some years you can
also reach out to me through my company
Nimble Pros uh it's like nimble
professionals and we're happy to talk to
you about your questions about how to
get better as a team or how to write
better software or assess the software
that you have and see you know what are
those low hanging fruit that that we
could tweak that'll get you most of the
of the gains that you're looking for
cool well Steve thank you so much for
joining me on the show thank you it's
great to be here this is Jeff dittle for
software engineering radio thanks for
listening thanks for listening to se
radio an educational program brought to
you by it e software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our we s it at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under Creative Commons
license
2.5 thanks for listening